<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Re]stitucyon shulde be made.</title>
            <author>Basilica di San Pietro in Vaticano.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1518</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14077c.103A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide Harl.5919[132]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123870</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99892694</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99892694</idno>
            <idno type="VID">199938</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14122)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199938)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; E1:1[87b])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Re]stitucyon shulde be made.</title>
                  <author>Basilica di San Pietro in Vaticano.</author>
                  <author>Catholic Church. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Rychardus Pynson regius impressor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1518?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A version of STC 14077c.102, Artycles of the great indulgence of plenary remissyon.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: only known copy; bottom half of sheet only, with STC 14077c.150 on verso; incorrectly mounted with top half of STC 14077c.88.</note>
                  <note>Last paragraph begins: Also our soueraygne lorde kyng Henry the .viii.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="lat">lat</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Indulgences --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:199938:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtitucyon ſhulde be made.</p>
            <p>¶ Alſo yf any man and woman haue byn maryed togyder vnlaufully by reaſon of conſanguinyte or of affinite carnall or ſpyrituall / or through any other impedyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd prouynciall and his commyſſaries may dyſpence with them / ſo that they ſhall laufully contynue maryed:
<note place="margin">In cauſes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymony.</note> and their chyldren ſhalbe legittimate yf the cauſe haue nat ben promoted to the lawe.</p>
            <p>¶ Alſo the ſayd prouynciall of the friers Auguſtines by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myſſion of our ſayd mooſt holy father y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope hath full power and aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte to execute all theſe faculties in euery tyme and place as he ſhall be requyred / and his deputes in tyme of the pardon.
<note place="margin">The auctorite of the prouynciall or. gen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſary.</note>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Item the ſayd prouynciall hath aucthorite by hymſelfe &amp; by his ſubſtitutes to gyue letters called confeſſionalles in parchement ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the ſayd prouynciall by vertu wherof the receyuers of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may at all tymes duryng theyr naturall lyues / choſe an auble preeſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer or reguler to theyr confeſſour / which may aſſoyle them in caſes nat reſerued to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope / as often as they wyll.
<note place="margin">Of letters called co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſionalles &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentes of the ſame.</note> And alſo in caſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to the pope and nat contayned in the bull vſed to be reed at Rhome in cena dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i ones in theyr lyfe / and as often as they be in peryll of deth / and to chaunge all vowes into this &amp; other good warkes / and to releaſe all othes without preiudyce of any other perſon.</p>
            <p>¶ Item ſuche perſons as haue thoſe letters called confeſſionalles / may haue and vſe an aulter called Altare portatile / wherupon they may haue maſſe and other dyuine ſeruyce in places co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenyent / and alſo before day:
<note place="margin">To haue Altare portatile.</note> and in tyme of interdyction.</p>
            <p>¶ <note place="margin">To eate whyte me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in lent.</note> Item ſuche perſons may eate cheſe butter / and egges: and all other white meates in tyme of lent / frely and laufully: and alſo by the counſell of theyr gooſtly father / and of theyr phyſician they may eate fleſſhe / without ſcrupuloſite of conſcience.</p>
            <p>¶ Item euery ſuche perſon vyſiting any church or chapell in ſuche tymes as any ſtacions ben celebrate at Rhome / and knelyng ſay. v. Paternoſters.
<note place="margin">The ſtacyons of Rhome.</note> v. Aues. ſhall haue all and ſinguler indulgences / pardons / and plenary remyſſions: as he ſhulde haue yf he dyde vyſet the churches and ſtacyons perſonally within and without the holy cytie of Rhome. And euery ꝑſon receyuing ſuche letters ben admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a brother or ſyſter of the ſayd relygion for euermore.</p>
            <p>¶ If the ſayd Prouynciall be hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe or be his ſubſtitutꝭ gyueth letters of ꝑdon in paper nat ſealed / wherby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receyuers ſhall enioye all the ſayd priuileges &amp; facultis except etyng of whyte meates in lent / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of an aulter Portatile / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mutacion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .iiii.
<note place="margin">Of other letters of pardon.</note> pricypall vowes.</p>
            <p>¶ Item to euery man and woman beyng alyue or deed for whom any maſſe is ſayd or done in any day or tyme / at any of .ii.
<note place="margin">Aulters named ſea la celi.</note> aulters aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by the popes holy aucthorite for Scala celi within any church or chapell of the ſayd friers Auguſtins / the ſame Indulgence / ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don / and plenary remyſſion is graunted that they ſhulde haue / if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame maſſes were ſayd &amp; done for them within the churches of ſaint Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lateranenſe and Scala celi at Rhome / and ſuche priuyleged pardon aulters there ben .C.xxx.
<note place="margin">Suffrages graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the brothers &amp; ſiſters of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yd relygion.</note> In .lxv. places of the ſame religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offriers Auguſtins in englande &amp; Irelande / at the which aulters ben daylie ſayd a. M. maſſes for the lyues and ſoules of the bretherne and ſyſters: and other benefactours of the ſayd religion. With many other great priuileges / pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / graces / and indulgences graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto brothers and ſyſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd fryers Auguſtines by the holy fathers pope Sixtus the .iiii. pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the .viii. pope Iuly the ſeconde. And graciouſly confirmed by our holy father pope Leo that nowe is.</p>
            <p>¶ Item our holy father co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth by his bull vnder leade to all Archebyſſhoppes byſſhopes / prelates:
<note place="margin">The popis holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement.</note> &amp; all other men of holy church that they ſhall declare or cauſe to be declared all ſuche Indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces &amp; plenary remiſſyons as is grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to the ſayd church of ſaynt Peter and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy relygion wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhalbe requyred without any delay nat requyring any thing for their labours / ſub pena exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>icationis.</p>
            <p>¶ Alſo our ſoueraygne lorde kyng Henry the .viii.
<note place="margin">The kynges graci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous protection.</note> hath gyuen out his pate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t letters vnder his brode ſeale to all that be his true lege peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple / fauorably to receyu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the proctours &amp; meſſangers of the ſayd church of ſaynt Peter &amp; of the ſayd relygion. And ferthermore he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to all heed offycers / as Mayres / ſhyriffes balyes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtables and church wardens: of euery cytie / borowe / and towne / aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well within the lyberties as without / that they ſhuld gather y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuocyon &amp; charite of well dyſpoſed people in their paryſſh churches at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruyce tyme: aſſone as it is declared vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by their curate and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> money to be deliuerd to the ſayd proctours or meſſangers or any of their aſſignes. Theſe premiſſes well conſydred / bleſſed ſhall they be that helpe to promote this pardon of ſaynt Peter / and wo ſhalbe to the hynderers therof before the dredefull Iudge.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Rychardus Pynſon regius impreſſor.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>¶ God ſaue the kyng.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
